(upbeat music)
- Low English learners, welcome back to
another lesson with us here at English Pod.
My name is Marco.
- And I'm Erica.
- And today we're gonna
be talking about physics.
- That's right.
And advanced lesson for all
you physics lovers out there.
And even for those of you
who maybe don't love physics
so much, there's still
some great language here.
- Right, we're gonna be talking
about the big bang theory
of a very popular theory
of how the universe or
the world and how we
came upon being created.
- That's right, so we've
got some physics language.
But we've also got some really tough words
that I bet many of our
users have never seen before,
which we're gonna look
at those in this lesson.
- All right, so why don't we get started
with this great and interesting lesson
and let's listen to the
dialogue for the first time?
(upbeat music)
- What's up, you don't look too good?
- Yeah, my head hurts, that's all.
I've been physics
class all day, it's killer.
- I like physics, it's all math really,
arcs, curves, velocity, cool stuff.
- Yeah, yeah.
But today's lesson was all
about the creation of the universe.
- A physics class about
the creation of the universe.
That's some pretty
unscientific language there.
Sounds more religious to me.
- It's all religion.
Take the theory of the big bang.
How is it possible that all of the stuff in
the universe comes from an explosion?
That's no better than
Atlas carrying the globe on
his back or African myths
about turtles and stuff?
Turtles, whatever, look.
All that's required for
the creation of matter
is an imbalance of
particles and antiparticles.
At least that's what the math says.
- Math schmath, what's the evidence?
- There is evidence, you know Edwin Hubble,
the guy who in the early 20th century
was the first scientist to
measure the drift of matter
in the universe, thus advancing
notions of an expanding universe.
What would it be expanding from?
Well, the big bang, duh.
- Anyway, it's just a theory.
Why do people go around touting theories?
Where's the rigor in that?
- Dude, don't equivocate.
A theory only becomes a theory
after withstanding rigorous testing.
You slept through class, didn't you?
- You're making my head hurt again.
Quit with a question.
(laughing)
(upbeat music)
- Well, it sure does sound
like a difficult class, doesn't it?
- It's a very interesting
topic and very
controversial, so there
are many opinions on it.
But before we get into that, why don't
we take a look at some of those physics
related words that we listen
to in language takeaway?
- Language takeaway.
We've got four words, we've heard in the
dialogue, they're all related to physics.
So let's start with the
first one, which is matter.
- Matter, matter.
- Okay, so you probably know this word
from, what's the matter, what's wrong?
- Right, yep.
- In this case, we're talking about matter,
so anything that occupies space that
has a mass or that is related to energy.
So matter.
- So all things in the world
are made up of matter, right?
- Exactly.
- Okay.
- Now let's move on to another one.
- Particles. - Particles.
- Particles.
- Now, particles are a little bit more,
it's now particles are a little bit easier.
They're just very small pieces of a hole.
- An apple is made up of apple particles?
- Something like that.
If you wanna understand it easily,
yeah, you apple has many small
particles that make up the apple.
So like, let's paint a picture here.
Imagine you've got a beach and all the
pieces of sand are particles of the beach.
- Exactly, very good.
So those are particles.
- Now, the next one is a
little bit difficult for me.
I don't understand this.
Anti-particles.
- All right, so anti-particles.
- Anti-particles.
- Now this prefix, anti.
It means something that is against, right?
- Right.
- I've seen this one in anti-clockwise.
- All right, so anti-particles are
those that are against particles.
So basically, if you have a particle
that has a positive charge
and another one comes in
with a negative charge in the same
weight and the same type of particle,
if they get together, they cancel
each other out and they both die.
- Oh.
- So that's an anti-particle.
- All right, well, you heard
it first year at English hot.
So anti-particles are not a
good thing to have around.
- Now we also heard them talk about the drift of matter.
- Right, drift of matter.
- Drift of matter.
- Also sometimes called
drift of dark matter.
- Okay, well, I know
the verb too drift, right?
To sort of float away on the sea.
- Right, if you have a little ship, you
leave it on the beach, it'll drift away.
It'll go slowly away.
- Yeah.
- But what about drift of matter?
- So basically the drift
of matter is this residue,
the remains of the big
bang of the explosion.
- Okay.
- So matter and radiation keeps
on drifting through the universe.
- So it's moving slowly
through the universe.
- So moving slowly, so this
big explosion and just consider
it to be like this ripple and
it's expanding and expanding.
That's the drift of matter.
- All right, well, I learned
something else today.
- Some very specific
words related to physics,
but it's very interesting
once you get into reading
about these things, it will
help you to understand it better.
- That's right.
- But we've also got some
non-physics-related language
that we wanna look at now
in language takeaway part two.
- Language takeaway.
- Drift of matter and how it's
drifting through the universe.
And he said, thus advancing the
notions of an expanding universe.
- So I wanna look at the
phrase, thus advancing notions.
- Thus advancing notions.
- Okay, let's start with
the first word here, thus.
- Okay, so this is a good
connector or conjunction
or conjunction and basically it means,
therefore, therefore or in consequence, right?
- So thus advancing notions.
Now notions are ideas.
- Right.
- And so when you advance notions or
advance ideas, you help them make progress.
You help them go forward and become known.
- Okay, so in order to
understand this in the
context, they are saying
that the drift of matter,
thus advances notions
of an expanding universe.
So it is making progress to people believing
that the universe is getting bigger.
- Okay, so interesting phrase.
Now, I really like this word, thus,
and a lot of people are afraid to use it.
So why don't we hear a few
examples of how it's used in context?
- Example one.
So you can see that we've
studied the fossil record,
and thus we can conclude
that evolution is a fact.
- Example two.
- He broke severe company
policies, thus we had to fire him.
- Example three.
I did not receive the documents on time,
thus I was unable to send them to you.
- All right, good examples of thus,
and I guess now we can
use it a little bit better.
- That's right.
- Now let's move on to our next word.
So they were talking about people
who go around touting theories.
- Tout.
- To tout.
- Okay, so what does this mean tout?
- Well, basically, when you
tout something, you talk about
it in a positive way, so as
to almost like sell that thing.
- Okay.
- So for example, we can say,
the company is touting the
many benefits of its product.
- Okay, very good.
So to talk positively about something.
- Yeah, what the idea
of trying to sell that
thing or make people
buy into it or believe it.
- All right, very good.
What about our next word?
- Well, we heard two
related words in the dialogue.
They were talking about where's the rigor
in these theories and rigorous testing.
- Okay, so what's the difference
between rigor and rigor?
- Rigor is the state of being
very clear and careful and exact.
- Okay.
- And rigorous is just the adjective, clear,
careful, attention to detail and exact.
- Okay, very good.
So rigorous training.
- I'm going over my
notes in rigorous detail.
- Okay, very good.
And now we have one more word today in
language takeaway and that is equivocate.
- So we heard, dude, don't equivocate.
- Don't equivocate.
All right, so what does he mean by this?
- Well, when you equivocate, you use
big words to try and mislead somebody.
- Okay, so using big words
to confuse or to mislead.
- Yep, so for example, we
could say the job candidate.
And we could say when asked about his
experience, the job candidate equivocated.
- Okay.
- Or even the presidential nominee
did not equivocate when
he explained his tax policy.
- All right, so some good
examples, good phrases,
a lot of interesting stuff and a little
bit more educational podcast today.
- That's right, so let's
continue with our education
by listening to the
dialogue one last time.
(upbeat music)
- What's up?
You don't look too good.
- Yeah, my head hurts, that's all.
I've been a physics
class all day, it's killer.
- I like physics, it's all math, really,
arcs, curves, velocity, cool stuff.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
- But today's lesson was all
about the creation of the universe.
- A physics class about
the creation of the universe.
That's some pretty
unscientific language there.
Sounds more religious to me.
- It's all religion.
Take the theory of the big bang.
How is it possible that all of the stuff in
the universe comes from an explosion?
That's no better than
atlas carrying the globe on
his back or African myths
about turtles and stuff.
- Turtles, whatever, look.
All that's required for
the creation of matter
is an imbalance of
particles and antiparticles.
At least that's what the math says.
Math, schmath, what's the evidence?
- There is evidence, you know Edwin Hubble,
the guy who in the early 20th century
was the first scientist to
measure the drift of matter
in the universe, thus advancing
notions of an expanding universe.
What would it be expanding from?
Well, the big bang, duh.
- Anyway, it's just a theory.
Why do people go around touting theories?
Where's the rigor in that?
- Dude, don't equivocate.
A theory only becomes a theory
after with standing rigorous testing.
He slept through class, didn't you?
- You're making my head hurt again.
Quit with a question.
(upbeat music)
- All right, so the big bang
theory, very controversial.
In some schools in the United States,
they have prohibited the
teachers from teaching it.
- I know, which is,
seems quite interesting
to me, but it is actually
very controversial
and people can get really,
really upset about this in America.
So it is an interesting topic.
Take it from the point
of view of just something
else, maybe just to
learn a little bit more
about this topic, such as physics, right?
- Right, but there's something
that is uncontroversial,
but I did wanna talk about now
that we heard in the dialogue.
There's a lot of really
interesting sort of
slang words here in
the dialogue, isn't there?
- Yeah, we heard in the
first part of the dialogue
when he said, "I've been
in physics class all day.
" Killer, killer.
So what does he mean by killer?
- Oh, he's just basically
saying it's really hard.
You know, it's like, it's so
difficult that it's murderous.
- It was intense.
- Yep.
- But this word we can use
positively as well, can't we?
- Yeah, I guess you could
say that was a killer party.
- Yeah, killer moves on the dance floor.
- Okay.
- Another interesting thing is
that he said, math, schmaph.
- Now schmaph isn't really a word.
- No, but this is a
really common structure.
We use in English when we want to sort of
take away from the importance of an idea.
- Okay, so you're
saying it's not important.
I don't care about it or it's not worth it.
- Yeah, so for example, I'm on a diet.
- Right, and I would say diet schmia.
- Yeah.
- So basically the structure is just added
S-H and then just kind of make it rhyme.
- Yeah.
- Schmia or like, like, work, mark.
- Yeah, work, schmirk
or something like that.
So you're just making fun of it
and you're taking away importance.
- Yeah, that's a pretty neat phrase.
And one more, we heard them say duh, duh.
So when we say this, we're just
saying like, you should know this stupid.
- Yeah, this is obvious.
- Yep.
- It's kind of making fun of the person
or just saying it's so obvious
how can you not know it.
- Yeah, and it always goes either at
the beginning or at the end of a sentence.
- Yeah, so duh, Marco,
we're recording a podcast.
- Right, very good.
So some great words and
phrases in this dialogue and a little
bit of slang as well so you can
use it maybe with your friends.
- That's right.
If you have any questions about
the language in this dialogue
or any thoughts on physics
or the Big Bang Theory,
come and check out our
website at EnglishPod.com.
- All right, we'll see you
guys there and until next time.
- Goodbye, bye.
(upbeat music)